Film Production and Distribution presents
Film Production and Distribution presents
JÁNOŠÍK
JáNO?íK
Music: Tibor Andrašovan
Music: Tibor Andraovan
Editor: Maximilián Remen Sound: Bohumil Brunclík
Editor: Maximilián Reme Sound: Bohumil Brunclík
Staring
Staring
Cast:
Cast:
Produced by Studio of Feature films Bratislava - Koliba
Produced by Studio of Feature films Bratislava - Koliba
Executive producer:
Executive producer:
Director of photography:
Director of photography:
Screenplay by and directed by:
Screenplay by and directed by:
2nd EPOCH
2nd EPOCH
Send Huncaj, to bring the saw!
让Huncaj把锯条拿过来
- What is father Uhorcík cooking? - What else? A ram!
- Uhor?ík老爹在煮什么？ - 还能是啥？一只羊！
Swords and axes are of no use here, we need barrels of gunpowder.
剑和斧头在这里都没有用 我们需要一桶一桶的火药
l will hit the provincial gunpowder storage.
我会去袭击省火药库
For whom are you preparing that gibbet-loop, Brute?
Brute你在为谁准备这绞索呢？
Who knows, maybe for my own head.
谁知道呢，也许就为我自己的脑袋吧
For you l am going to make a nicer one, l´ll take your measures!
因为你我成为了一个好人， 所以我会听从你的指示
Weak! The lords are preparing a hook for me!
哈哈！贵族们在为我准备绞索
Ropemaker...
你在做绳子
Chop! l will chop three of you down.
砍！我会把你们三个砍倒
lndeed, aiming is the most important when shooting.
射击的时候，瞄准是最重要的
Not the target... that goes by itself.
不是目标，他会自己出现
l only looked at it and booom!
我只是看到了他，然后就“砰”
And the soldier, rolled over!
然后，士兵就倒下了
Such a shooter am l!
我很厉害吧！
l saw that, father!
我看到了，老爹
l don´t know if the captain appoints me the main shooter.
不知道队长是否让我成为首席射手
l will shoot a swallow in flight and a stag in the valley.
我可以射到在飞的燕子， 还有山谷中的牡鹿
l bet, you´ve shoot today again... a ram.
我猜你今天又开枪了・・・ 又是公羊
You can´t cook anything else.
你就不能做点其他东西
Don´t croak, you Liptov´s menace!
不要叫了，Liptov的危险人物！
You never even smelled a Turkish style ram.
你从来没有闻到过真正的土耳其公羊
They say you fed your men with frogs!
他们说你拿青蛙给你的手下们吃
What you... !
什么！
Three men under the camp! Michalec, go see!
有三个人在营地下面， Michalec，去看看！
Catch me!
快接住我，我来了！
- Why are you screaming? - Your blanket is ready!
- 你喊什么啊？ - 已经准备好了！
Where did you find it?
你们在哪里找到的？
Come, drag these altarboys, l am out of breath.
来，拉一把这些小伙子们， 我气都喘不过来了
- What religion are they? - Polish gorals. Can´t you see the beauty?
- 他们从哪里来？ - 波兰来的喜马拉雅斑羚，你没发现他们很漂亮？
Look, they even go robbing with an eagle´s feather in their hats.
看，他们的帽子上还有老鹰的羽毛
Come, we´ll rattle for you, they´ll inquire you up there.
来，我们先带你们过去， 他们会在那上边询问你们
We´re sending our greetings to heaven!
我们在往天上走！
Look, Gajdošík found some Polish twins.
看, Gajdosik带来了波兰的两兄弟
They got tired of Polish poverty so they came to the Slovaks to be poor.
他们厌烦了在波兰的贫困生活， 所以到这里过新的贫困生活
They cried until now, they´ll moan from now on.
他们从前哭到现在， 又会继续哭下去
- Seize! - Secure it, fellows!
- 抓好了！ - 抓稳，伙计！
Lift your feet, you are entering the free land.
迈出脚步，你们进入了自由之地
This way.
跟我来
Olders to the captain!
年长的人到队长那里去
Always the olders only! l am old, but they are not calling me.
每次都叫年长的人！ 我也是老人，但是从来没叫我
Just because you are old.
就因为你太老了
Older also means wiser.
年长意味着智慧
Father Uhorcík, to the captain!
Uhor?ík老爹，去队长那里！
Out of the way! The captain calls the wise men.
让开，队长在叫有智慧的人去
You came here voluntarily to make justice in this crooked world by an axe.
你们自愿来到这里， 是为了在这个扭曲的世界上用斧头实现正义
And so, like we did, swear in front of the elders on the axe!
那么现在，像我们以前一样， 在年长的人面前发誓
Put your hands here. You too!
把手放到斧头上，你也是
We swear in front of the faces of the elders...
我们在年长的人面前发誓・・・
that we will never spill innocent blood...
我们绝不伤害无辜者
we won´t give away bandits´ secrets, not even if tortured...
我们不会放过强盗，不会说出秘密， 即使我们遭到折磨
and if necessary, we will sacrifice our lives for our friends.
如有必要，我们会为伙伴牺牲自己
This we swear!
我们发誓！
Welcome, brothers!
欢迎你们，兄弟们！
Welcome!
欢迎！
Father, pour the wine!
老爹，你来洒这些酒
- Let´s proceed to God´s table. - Pity that we don´t swear every day.
- 我们来到上帝的桌前 - 可惜我们不是每天都有宣誓
- Wait, one by one! - So, first to the newcomers.
- 不要急，一个一个来 - 从新来的人开始
- And to the captain! - That´s how it should be!
- 为了队长！ - 本该如此！
l am coming! For God´s sake, who is it at this hour?
我来了！看在上帝份上，谁会这么晚来？
l´m coming, coming!
我就来！
Good evening, father.
晚上好，神父
So bad... like this, with a weapon.
糟糕的会面，像这样，你还带着武器
Leave! Bad luck follows you.
快走吧，你会带来霉运的
We don´t have any peace anymore, the lords haunt, beat, torture us.
We don't have any peace anymore, the lords haunt, beat, torture us. 我们很久没有安稳过了， 这些贵族常出现，打我们，折磨我们
That´s why l´m looking for the count.
所以我才来找他们
We are withering away, we cannot even say mass anymore.
我们已经不行了， 甚至再不能说太多话了
They say we are being noisy in the church.
他们说我们在教堂太吵闹了
Where did count Aurel go?
Aurel到哪里去了？
What, are you going to set a fire?
什么，你还想放火？
By heart! Not by fire, son!
用心！而不要用火，儿子！
Aurel went to Orava!
Aurel去了Orava
Go and burn him! He has two more mansions! Who are you going to harm?
去烧了他！他又有两个庄园了！ 你们到底在伤害谁？
They make the peasants rebuild every mansion and farm that was set on fire!
他们让农民重新修你们烧过的房子，农场
They will not build it again! Tell them.
叫他们不要修了！
Whisper, give them advice at confession.
他们忏悔的时候告诉他们
Burn hearts with hearts! There is no prayer more beautiful!
用心去点燃心！ 没有更好的祈祷了
Forgive me, Father, l know, that you are with us.
原谅我，神父， 我知道你是和我们一起的
Here!
这里！
Give it to the poor as they need.
把这些给需要的人
Oh my God! l will not touch stolen money!
上帝！我不会碰偷来的钱
lt´s the money of the peasants!
这本来就是农民的钱！
l´ve sheltered her. Soldiers were trying to breakin to her place twice already in the night.
我把她藏着，士兵已经两次试图在晚上闯进她家了
Jurko, if you only knew...
Jurko，你只要知道
You should go away somewhere.
你得离开这里
Dress up, Tereza. l will find a safe place for you.
穿好衣服，Tereza， 我会把你带到安全的地方
Protect her. She suffers for Jánošík´s bandits.
保护好她，他一直因为你们这些强盗受苦
Be good, son.
好自为之，孩子
Night has never been so short for me.
夜晚从来没像现在这样短暂
Once... l wasn´t young anymore... l was going with you.
我曾梦到过，当我老的时候， 和你在一起
l was dreaming. l was walking with you on the lake.
我和你在湖边散步
l´ve never seen anything like it in my life. A lake like from a fairy-tale.
我从来没有见过的景色， 那湖就像童话故事所说的一样。
We flew easily over the water.
我们轻轻地飞过湖面
l can not even tell.
我无法描述出来了
Suddenly you caught my elbow and said: Tereza, you are crying!
突然间，你抓住我的胳膊说： Tereza，你在哭
But l was not crying because it was only a dream.
但是我没有，因为那只是梦
Now tell me what you want, or otherwise l will really start crying.
现在告诉我你想要什么？ 不然我真的要哭了
But you know everything already.
你已经知道了啊
l stray, seeking water like a thirsty stag.
我迷路了，像只口渴的小鹿在找水喝
Go alone. Give my greeting to Quail, l am sending her the help l promised.
去吧，代我问候Quail， 我保证会帮助她的
Go!
去吧
Give the cows to the people! And the flour too!
把牛群和面粉带给人们！
We will, youngster!
没问题，小伙子们！
lf you´ll meet soldiers, send them to us!
如果遇到士兵，就带给我们
We should return to help them.
我们应该回去帮他们
Don´t worry, captain. My men are there!
不用担心，队长， 我的伙计们过去了
We won´t put ourselves to shame, six against six.
我们不能低估自己， 六对六正好
Well, that´s right.
这可正好
Get out of the way of the provincial judge!
滚开，不要挡省法官大人的路
l wonder where should l step back.
我在想我该怎么走开
Step aside, peasant worm!
滚一边去，蠢农民！
Don´t be silly, you puppet, they´re the count´s creatures.
别傻了，你这走狗， 这些是贵族的东西
How do you dare call me a puppet?
你竟敢叫我走狗？
Don´t beat him!
不要打他！
Don´t beat in front of a provincial judge!
不要在省法官大人面前打他！
Bring him up! We will judge.
带过来，我们会处理他
Who are you, father?
老爹，你是谁？
God´s son, my lord.
我是上帝的儿子，大人
Well, we are all God´s children. But whom do you serve?
我们当然都是上帝的儿子， 你的主人是谁？
l serve Jánošík, my lord.
我在侍奉Jáno?ík，大人
Not really serving, but helping Jánošík!
不是侍奉，我是在帮他！
l don´t know him.
我不知道他
Youngster, my lord!
是个年轻人
He gave this into my hand and said, bring the count´s flour to the people.
他要我把贵族的面粉给农民
Put it away!
拿开！
l will, l don´t even know, how to...
我会的，我甚至不知道怎么样...
Hands up, lordly dogs!
举起手来，你们这些贵族狗崽子！
Get down a get undressed. Move!
下来，把衣服脱了，快点！
Get down from the horses, or l will clean out your ears!
从马上下来，不然我把你耳朵割了
Nobody has ever kissed my hand in my life, so if you could...
从来没有人亲吻过我的手， 你能否这样？
Move on, or l will make a sieve out of you! Drop that gun!
快走，不然我要向你开火了！ 把枪放下！
This didn´t have to be...
这就不必了・・・
l should die if this is not arrogance!
这是严重的挑衅行为！
Just consider it, twenty cows!
想想，20头牛！
They steal twenty cows from you and send you such a message!
他们偷了你二十头牛还用这种方式告诉你
One or two, but twenty! l will feed a regiment with those!
不是一头两头，而是二十头！ 可以用来供养一个团的兵了
When are they going to eat it? What are they doing with it?
他们打算什么时候吃掉？ 他们打算怎么用？
You have it in that message, papa.
爸爸，信里面有说
Thank you very much. We will give it to the people. Signed Jánošík.
非常感谢你，我们会把它们分给大家的， Jáno?ík
- Have you ever heard that name? - l don´t remember.
- 你听说过这个名字吗？ - 我记不得了
Your majesty!
尊敬的各位！
We, our property... Four of us stand for the power of this province!
我们的财产・・・ 我们四个人要为这个省的秩序而战
You four stand for nothing without soldiers.
没有兵力，你们什么都不是
Stop it, property is concerned here!
别说了，要考虑我们的财产
The wisest thing to do is to offer a reward for the head of that...
最聪明的方式是拿一笔钱悬赏那谁的头・・・
Jánošík.
Jáno?ík.
That is why l´ve called the provincial judge.
所以我请来了省法官
Judge knows better, let him give us advice!
法官更有见识，听听他的建议
Horrible! So much property! Twenty cows!
太可怕了！如此多财产！ 二十头牛！
We´ll call the lords, we´ll send out messengers, we´ll summon a convention and...
我们会召集附近的贵族，要派出我们的信使， 要召开一个会议
But not into my house! l won´t let them eat all my bread!
可不能在我这里， 我可不想让他们白吃我的东西！
We´ll go to the bishop.
我们去主教那里
He cannot keep the faithful in order, so let him suffer!
他不能让信众服从秩序， 所以要让他吃点亏
This is not meant for your nerves.
这个恐怕你们会受不了
Please, come in the boudoir.
请到闺房去休息
Let´s rest a little bit.
我们休息一下
The provincial judge comes!
省法官大人来了！
Thank God! l am going to greet him!
感谢上帝，我去迎接他
- You will see, the judge will find them. - Whom?
- 你们会看到的，法官大人会找到它们 - 什么？
- Your cows. - How?
- 你的牛 - 怎么找？
He can distinguish between a lordly and a regular cow!
他会区分贵族的牛和普通的牛！
How?
怎么做到？
- ln fact, beef is beef. - Yes, it is!
- 事实上，牛肉就是牛肉 - 就是这样！
Oh my God, where did this happen to you?
天啊，发生了什么事情？
On a straight road.
在一条道上
They shaved me like this!
他们这样羞辱了我！
The chain is gone, the rings are gone! They left me without a penny.
项链不在了！戒指也没了！ 一分钱都没给我剩！
They have me...
他们让我・・・
Bandits! And they put this into my hand.
强盗！他们把这个放我手里！
- Bandits? - Attacking the provincial judge?
- 强盗？ - 袭击省法官？
- And what happened with your soldiers? - Gone...
- 你的士兵呢？ - 都跑了・・・
Maybe they are already hung on the trees.
也许已经在树上吊死了
- How dare they! - What happened to the world we live in?
- 他们怎么敢！ - 这个世界发生了什么？
lt is horrible just to listen to it.
听着就已经够恐怖了
Jánošík again.
又是Jáno?ík
Clever man. At least he won´t rot as we will.
他足够聪明，至少他不会像我们一样堕落
lt is a jay, not a hen! Bring a bigger one!
是只松鸡，不是母鸡！ 要个大的！
Where should l get one? You´ve already taken ten from me.
我从哪里给你找？ 你已经拿了十只去了
Don´t squawk! lf the lord prepares a wedding, he can take a pig as well!
不要发牢骚！要是主人要结婚， 一头猪都得交出来
But he´s only preparing an engagement!
但是这次只不过是订婚
lt doesn´t matter! Quiet! Eggs there. Next!
不要废话！给我安静！鸡蛋放这，下一个！
Greedy peasants! Jánošík on you!
贪婪的人，Jáno?ík会惩罚你！
Jánošík? He doesn´t know about us
Jáno?ík？他并不认识我们
He will. Jánošík will learn about everything.
他会的，Jáno?ík什么都会知道的
- Why are you not taking it? - That one is too thin!
- 你们为什么不带走这个？ - 太瘦了
Damn her ass, if she´s thin!
你看它屁股，怎么会瘦！
Catch that goose, scoundrel!
抓住这只鹅，你这个无赖！
We should sweeten up that wedding.
我们应该去参加这婚礼
At least eight count families will gather there.
至少八个贵族家庭会来
So much drink and food.
会有很多吃的喝的
They will all have to pass under Strecno to Pongrac´s mansion!
他们必须通过Strecno才能到达Pongrac的庄园
Every carriage will be followed by at least ten soldiers.
每个马车至少会有十个士兵护送
Not power, but wit will decide.
要靠智慧，光有力气是不够的
All counts should be taken by the devil! Aurel is lost somewhere!
所有贵族都应该被魔鬼带走！ Aurel似乎不见了！
He will come there!
他会出现的！
One who gets Aurel, can open a bottle of tokai!
谁抓到Aurel， 就能开一瓶tokai葡萄酒
That´s the word! Let´s go!
太好了！我们走！
l am going to meet Aurel, bring the lords to the upper meadow!
我去见Aurel，你带贵族们去上面的草地
You can depend on me, captain!
交给我吧，队长！
Take them!
拦截他们！
Welcome, now you are all in the same boat!
欢迎你们，你们逃不掉了！
Stop!
停下！
Don´t scream, witch!
不要叫，婊子们！
- They´re coming! - Come on, start working!
- 他们来了！ - 来，开始干吧！
- You there! What is it? - A hole. We are repairing.
- 嘿！你们在做什么？ - 一个洞，我们在修补
Speed it up then, we´re in a hurry!
快点，我们有急事
We are too! But without any help, it´ll take an hour or two...
我们也是！但是没有帮手， 恐怕要一两个小时
Get down! Throw them those sticks!
下来！帮他们搬木材
And move on, so we won´t have to stay here until the evening.
快点，不然我们会在这里一晚上
You face Hrajnoha! Put it down and work!
你们遇到了Hrajnoha，哈哈! 放下来！
Let´s go!
我们走
l don´t understand. We are going to a wedding... calmly...
我不明白怎么回事， 我们要去参加婚礼
l understand. Please, would you kindly remember where count Aurel is?
我知道，请你告诉我，Aurel在哪里？
ln my son´s carriage. Somewhere behind us... over there!
在我儿子的马车里 在后面，已经来了
More fires, Aurel.
还有子弹，Aurel
Stop!
停下来！
The horse!
马不要走了
How much is a peasant in your region?
你这里一个农民多少钱？
- My father wants 500, l do 1 ,000 ducats. - l´ve got two pipes loaded.
- 我父亲想要500金币，我觉得值1000 - 我带了两包
- Easy math. You will pay me 3,000. - Thief!
- 很好算，你要给我3000 - 你这是讹诈
- Sending my greetings to Jánošík! - What a hero!
- 帮我问候Jáno?ík - 他可真是个英雄
Run back home!
回家去！
Why did you... lie?
你这个骗子・・・
How do they only tremble, porcelain dolls... Move down!
怎么他们只会颤抖， 瓷娃娃们，下来！
Gentlemen, be reasonable!
请讲讲道理！
Are your legs petrified or what? Get out of the carriage!
你的脚是石化了还是怎么了？ 快下来！
Get down and run home!
下来，滚回家去！
Be reasonable, gentlemen!
请讲讲道理！
Move up, puppet!
快走！
Everything all right, only Aurel is lost.
一切正常，但是Aurel不见了
Oh, he isn´t lost! Come!
他还没丢！快跟上！
Don´t be scared, noble lordships!
不用怕，高贵的阁下
What you give up, you´ll give up to God, you will see it no more!
你失去的东西，都给了上帝， 你再也别想拿回去！
Another count for offering!
下一个！
Old lady and young Miss too, give something to dowry!
不管是夫人还是小姐， 都交出嫁妆
This is that devil that has stolen my pearls!
就是你这魔鬼，抢了我的珍珠！
Don´t scream old one, or you´ll get a bad throat!
不要叫唤，老女人， 小心挨打
Come, we´ll take care of yo
过来，我们会看着你
Scandal, that is such impertinence
太无礼了，简直是耻辱
l do not wear jewels when l travel.
我路上不戴首饰的
Clothes off!
衣服脱了！
- lt´s unnecessary, l´ll search myself. - All right, search then.
- 算了，还是我自己来吧 - 好吧
There you see!
休想耍滑头！
Next!
下一个！
Come on! Pants down! Next!
裤子脱了！下一个！
Try it once without your servant´s help!
试一下没有仆人自己脱衣服吧！
lf they kindly died, the dust on the ground would be properly greased!
如果他们死了，地上的杂草可有肥料了
- What about him? - Cut his throat and fry!
- 怎么处理他？ - 割喉咙，然后炸！
You see!
你知道了吧！
Everything went smoothly, only one soldier is dead.
一切正常，只有一个士兵死了
Who killed him?
谁干的？
Should l´ve waited for him to kill me?
难道要我等他先杀了我？
No, Gajdošík.
不，Gajdosik
We said that we´re going to loot, not to kill!
我们说过只要财物，不能杀人
Choose good horses, burn the carriages and send the lordships home on foot!
选出好马，烧掉马车， 让贵族们走路回去
What count Pongrác prepared for these eaters, give it to peasants!
把Pongrac要给这些素餐者吃的东西都分给农民！
l don´t need gold, silver, not even a girlfriend.
我不需要金子，银子， 甚至女人
lf we only got wine more often.
只要有酒就行了
What is this going to be good for?
这些东西拿来做什么？
Some of us should get married.
我们中肯定有人想结婚的
l would decorate his bride with this so she wouldn´t be able to get to the altar.
我会用这些东西打扮他的新娘， 这些东西会沉得让她都走不到祭坛上
l would know what to do with my share.
我想知道我那份怎么样
l wouldn´t hang it on a woman.
我不会给女人的
Where would you find such a woman?
你在哪里去找女人？
She´d look at you and her head would spin.
她看着你，头就会发晕
She would dream of the devil for a month.
一个月都会睡觉梦到魔鬼
Better, when a woman dreams of the devil, than of gold!
梦到魔鬼总比她们梦到金子好！
Tell them to stop!
叫他们停下来
Let them be, we are not in a monastery.
随他们去吧，这里不是修道院
- We are catching mildew. - Damn mildew!
- 我们这是在堕落 - 去他的堕落
Pairing season is approaching! lt is always so.
大自然的交配季节要来了！ 这段时间总是这样的
When the stags start to rut, men smell women.
牡鹿发情的时候， 男人就会闻女人味
They need to be let among people more often.
他们需要经常一群人一起欢庆
l´m going for a scout. Rajcok reported foreign merchants.
我要出去侦查， Rajcok报告说有外国商人出现
l will stay down the whole night.
我整晚都会在这里
Skirts are best explored during the night!
只有晚上是掀裙子的时候！
And somebody will smash your mouth during a bright day!
白天这么做你会被打破脸
Lads! They´ve stuck to us and now they...
弟兄们！他们指责了我们但是他们自己却
Quiet! The captain can do whatever he wants
不要说了！队长可以做他想做的，
and decide however he wants! That´s the rule in the mountains!
并且决定他想做什么！ 这是这里的规矩
Ohh, poo-poo you...! l blew up.
哦・・・我闭嘴
lt is true! He has a girlfriend! That´s where he´s going!
他的确有女人， 所以他才要出去
And the his peasant´s shoes will shake!
那些农民会不安的
You should have warned him and instead of it you... We didn´t do anything!
你们应该警告他， 但是你们却什么都没做
- Gajdošík is... - Our death!
- Gajdosik有点 - 会害了我们的
l should have killed him long ago.
我早就该杀掉他
Take the cows away!
带上这些牛！
Mother, pick a cow,
大娘，选一头牛
the count has four hundred of them!
贵族们有四百头，哈哈！
Flour like snow. l´ve dreamt about such for years!
雪白的面粉，我可是盼了很多年了
One piece for each soul!
每人一盘
- Our captain gives everything away... - The captain can!
- 我们的队长把什么都给别人了・・・ - 他有权这么做！
You were too and you kept it. l don´t want to be in the mountains until the day l die.
你也是这样，我可不想在山上一直到死
You need to save something as well.
你也应该为自己存点东西
Don´t grumble. You´ve promised on the axe, so keep you mouth shut!
不要抱怨，你对着斧头发过誓言的！
Well, you get on with that oath!
好吧，你可真遵守诺言
Listen, l will jerk out your guts right away!
听着，我要把你内脏挖出来！
Why are you scaring my children in the night?!
你们为什么在晚上吓我的孩子？！
Oh, widow, don´t fuss!
哦，单身的母亲，不要这样
Widow or not widow! Why do you sneak around my yard in the night?
你管我是不是寡妇！ 你晚上在我院子里想要做什么？
We want to give you a cow.
我们想给你一头牛
- Count´s cow. - Just so?
- 贵族的牛 - 真的？
Our captain is like that, he takes form the count, gives to the poor.
我们的队长就是这样的，他从贵族哪里拿东西， 然后分给穷人
- And you are said to have a lot of kids. - A lot? Only seven!
- 而且据说你有很多孩子要养 - 很多？就七个！
Two cows go for seven.
七个小孩就分两头牛
Bring one more and bring a bag of flour as well!
再牵一头牛，然后领一袋面粉
Come on, Strakula...
来，Strakula
- And who is your captain? - Juro Jánošík.
- 你们队长是谁？ - Juro Jáno?ík
Our hope, God protect him!
我们的希望，上帝会保佑他！
God protect all of you, white falcons!
上帝会保护你们所有人，雄鹰们！
Don´t bother me, or l´ll hurt you!
不要这样，我会伤着你！
Well, the goal is the most important.
听我说，瞄准是最重要的
You take it like this, have a look like this, and... boom!
像这样拿好，然后瞄准，砰！
Damn you, the powder is wet!
妈的，火药打湿了
Go away! Can´t you see that l´m on guard!
走开！你们没看到我在站岗？
Father, you will make a hole in your stomach sooner or later.
老爹，你早晚会在你身上打一个洞
Here you go, play with the axe!
给你，拿着斧子
And who shot the soldier?
谁射到那个士兵的？
Get off, youngsters!
走开，小子！
- What was it? - The old man shot again.
- 怎么了？ - 那个老头又开枪了
- Jánošík isn´t back yet? - No.
- Jáno?ík还没回来 - 没有
lt´s hard to leave your girlfriend.
要离开女朋友，可不容易啊
- The emperor´s soldiers were here yesterday. - Upon my soul.
- 国王的士兵昨天来了 - 真的
And everything rests on my head! Call the elders!
我来决定，叫年长的人过来！
Krivy says: a lot of soldiers!
Krivy说有一大批士兵
How many? A lot is twenty but also two hundred!
多少？很多，是二十个还是两百个
l won´t leave my men to get beaten!
我不能让大家等着挨打
Or Krivy says: Merchant wagons come from Silesia!
Krivy也说了，商人们的货车从Silesia来了
How many of them, he doesn´t know.
但是不知道有多少辆
There is eight of those wagons, Rajcok says.
Rajcok报告说有八辆
Forty imperials go with them on the road.
有四十个士兵护送他们
We don´t know how many soldiers walk through the mountains.
我们不知道有多少士兵到山里
Captain, don´t test your luck with that one!
队长，不要冒险行事！
The emperor´s soldiers are killing on the spot!
他们正想杀人!
One who fears death, dies every day.
怕死的人，每天都像死了一样
You can stay at home, we won´t be splitting gold.
你可以留下来，我们不会把金子分了的
l don´t mind, you can sleep.
我不介意，你可以睡觉
But you are not sleeping well.
但是我肯定你睡不好
You are sleeping with the belt on your belly since long time ago!
你每天都穿着你的皮带睡觉
Reach into it, father!
老爹，看看里面有什么！
Come on, he doesn´t have hot coal or lizards in there!
你这是干嘛，里面可没有烧红的煤或者蜥蜴
Watch out, so you don´t poke your eye out.
看仔细了
Those are my beads!
是我的珠子！
You joined the group, bare-naked like a tree.
你既然加入了组织， 就不应该私藏东西
Pearls grow behind your belt.
你皮带上长着珍珠
Father, will you buy us something good to cook for that beauty?
老爹，麻烦你用这个去买些好东西来吃吧
Don´t give it to father! He´ll buy a ram again!
不要给他！ 他又会买羊！
lf he buys a ram, he´ll buy wine as well.
如果他买羊，他也会买酒的
Did you hear, father? Wine.
听到了吗？要酒
So you know what to spend those beads on.
你知道应该怎么花吧
- Oh well... - Wine...
- 不错 - 酒
- Where are you going? - Away.
- 去哪里？ - 随便走走
Good. You´ll go to scout with me.
好，你跟我一起去侦察
- You are commanding too much. - l don´t like to.
- 你管得太多了 - 我也不想
And suspect.
还要怀疑
Gajdošík is a bent man.
Gajdosik为人不可靠
But you shouldn´t have doubted him in front of all. That won´t straighten him.
但是你不应该在这么多人面前揭发他， 这样他也不会变好
lf you do not trust him, sack him!
如果不信任他，就让他走
l don´t trust him and l won´t sack him!
我是不相信他，但是不能让他走
l let him go and tomorrow we will all hang on a rope.
如果我赶他走，明天我们全会绞死
Whom of us do you trust at all?
我们中间你相信谁？
You the most, llcík.
当然是你，ll?ík
l´ve hurt you the most, and yet you didn´t abandon me.
我伤害了你，但是你没有离开我
- Do you know where are we going? - Following our nose.
- 我们去哪里？ - 凭感觉走吧
- There is a tavern up there. - l know. Tereza is up there.
- 前面有家小酒店 - 我知道，Tereza在那里
Everybody knows that. They are making jokes, when you are gone for too long.
谁都知道，只要你离开太久， 他们就会拿来开玩笑
- Tereza helps up. - lt depends.
- Tereza 可以帮忙 - 要看是谁了
Don´t you dare or l´ll...
你不要说了，不然我可・・・
Slowly... You wanted to say something else.
冷静，你想说点别的吧
l love Tereza.
我爱Tereza
l know better. She loves you. So what do you want?
我更清楚，她爱你， 你还想要怎么样？
- l feel blue. - Kill yourself.
- 我感到悲伤 - 算了吧
Nothing hurts me anymore. l left home to get over it faster.
我已经无所谓了，我离开家也可以更快忘记
- lt is all right now. - Did you leave only because of that?
- 现在已经好了 - 你只是因为这个才离开家？
Because of that too. Why to be in the way? You belong to each other, since childhood.
当然还有别的，为什么要这样呢？ 你们本来就是一对，从小就是
lf they´ll hang me, promise, that you will take care of Tereza!
如果我被绞死了，你一定要照顾好Tereza， 向我保证！
Fool! They´ll hang us both!
笨蛋，我们会一起被绞死！
- Good morning, Terka! - Good morning, boys!
- 早上好, Terka! - 早上好, 小伙子们!
- Come on, feed the wolves! - Welcome in here!
- 来喂这些狼 - 欢迎你们
Breakfast will be ready in a moment.
早餐很快就好
l don´t understand anything anymore.
我什么都不知道
Juro is a good man. He deserves you.
Juro配得上你
Don´t be angry at me.
不要生我的气
l´ve spent many nights crying, praying... nothing helped.
我已经哭了很多天了，还有祈祷， 但是没有用
- Good morning. - Oh, you are here already?
- 早上好 - 哦，你来了
- Good morning, bandit innkeeper! - How many soldiers are following you?
- 早上好，老板娘 - 你们后面跟了多少人？
We didn´t count them, Quail!
我们没有数，Quail
Can you see them? They come only when their girlfriends let them loose.
你看到他们了么？ 只有他们的女朋友放他们走才来
They didn´t sleep, they´re hungry, thirsty...
他们没有睡觉，又饿又渴
Because you are our sweetest. With you, honey is sweet as well!
你是我们中最甜的姑娘，就像蜂蜜
You rat, let go!
油嘴滑舌，放开我！
l will give them oat as soon as l´ll catch my breath again.
等我喘好气，我会喂它们燕麦
Do l hear Jánošík?
是Jáno?ík吗？
Yes, Granny. God bless you.
是我，奶奶，上帝祝福你
- May God do it! - Did you get up already?
- 但愿上帝会的 - 你已经起床了
- l did. A long time ago. - l´ve brought you something.
- 是啊，我很早就起来了 - 我给你带了些东西
You shouldn´t have bothered.
你不需要这么做
Have some sweets.
一些糖
- Oh God, gingerbread... - And cake too.
- 哦，是姜饼 - 还有蛋糕
- Hawkie, how can l pay it back to you? - You will say a prayer under my gallows!
- 雄鹰，我怎么回报你啊？ - 我在绞刑台上的时候，你要为我祈祷
Don´t blaspheme, son!
不要胡说，孩子
- Good morning, Granny! - llcík!
- 早上好，奶奶！ - 是ll?ík!
- You guessed right. - Quail, eat first and then go to sleep!
- 是我 - Quail, 吃完就去睡觉
We didn´t shut our eyes even for a while this night!
今天晚上我们要一直盯梢
As always. They only come snoring here!
和以前一样，他们来这里只会打鼾
l have a young ram on the pan!
锅里煮了只羊给你们
Oh my God! l am starting to shoot rams from now on.
上帝，我在这里就可以射山羊了
- l hear horses! - That´s ours in the backyard.
- 我听到马蹄声了 - 院子里面有我们的马
Not yours. Stranger´s horses!
不是你们的，是陌生的马蹄声！
We expected them for tomorrow.
我们以为他们明天到
Don´t even think of starting any fight in here!
不要想着在这里行动！
Come on up, bandit innkeepers, and cheerfully...
放轻松，老板娘・・・
Easy to say, be cheerful... and l will burn.
说起来容易，我紧张得不行了
Captain Bucko with his company!
Bucko队长和他的伙计！
We are waiting for you, Mister Bucko.
Bucko大人，我们期待你的到来很久了
l know, you are looking for Jánošík.
你们是要找Jánosík吧
You are on a good track. You´ll see him today.
你们算是来对了， 今天就可以看到他们
Finish, Mister! ldentify yourself!
等一下，请出示你的证件
Free Mister Pulchre with his spy.
独立官员Pulchre和侍从
Here is the seal of the provincial judge
这是省法官的信
and here is my gun. Take it.
这是我的枪，给你
Hand over your weapon and go out.
交出你的枪，然后出去
Come with me. l have a provincial order for you.
请来一下，有一个上级命令要给你
Trust for trust.
出于信任，
Five hundred ducats in gold.
这是500金币
They can be yours.
全都归你了
You have the soldiers, l know where Jánošík is.
你这里有兵力， 我知道Jánosík在哪里
But... it is very dangerous.
但是行动会很危险
My soldiers do not fear the devil himself.
我的手下可不怕
l would like to hear that from them.
我希望听听他们自己怎么说
- Come here. - What do you think about this?
- 过来 - 你们有什么想法？
Who doesn´t want a hole in the head, he shouldn´t stick it out!
要是不想脑袋开花，就不要出来
My llcík, where are you going to lay you bones down?
我的ll?ík，你到底要去哪里啊？
ln your yard, Quail, l swear!
就在你的院子里，我保证
- My dear. - l will wait for you by the road.
- 亲爱的 - 我在路上等你
Oh my dear, l can see blood dripping here soon.
天啊，这里马上就会流血
Martin, get the gun!
Martin，拿好枪
Line the blanket up!
拿开毯子！
Bow your heads, a wealthy merchant comes!
快低头鞠躬，有富豪来了
And eleven servants follow him!
还有十一个随从
- How much do you have in your pouch? - Empty store, hungry servant and hungry lord!
- 你们有多少钱？ - 什么都没有，穷贵族和穷仆人
- Catch a coin for the beggar! - Give my regards to Jánošík!
- 赏一个金币吧 - 向我问候Jánosík
- Greetings, journeymen! - Salute, captain.
- 你好！ - 敬礼，队长你好
Lure them into Vlcková, we´ll cut them off there!
把他们带进Vlckov？ 我们可以在那里拦截他们
We will, hay is already on the road!
好的，干草已经在路上了
Don´t lose your heads, don´t kill anyone!
不要丢了命，也不要杀人
Squadron, forward with attacking gallop!
中队听令，加快行军！
Yield behind the merchant carriages!
躲到商队后面去！
Grandfather, what´s up with you?
老爹，你怎么了？
- What happened to him? - He´s probably been wounded.
- 怎么了？ - 他受伤了
Poor man. What are we going to do with him?
唉，你打算怎么办？
- Move them! - Courage, we´re on for a loot!
- 搬走它们 - 打起精神，我们还要劫货！
Gee! Don´t fear the water, it´s only up to a frog´s belly!
快走，水就没过青蛙的腹部而已！
What´s up with you? Move them in the back there!
你在做什么？ 快让他们动起来
Damn it! Move you feet!
妈的，快动！
ln a line!
排好队！
Move those horses!
牵走这些马！
Oh, bandits, cheerfully!
强盗们，一起狂欢吧！
And l´m walking here and there, girls they miss me everywhere!
到处是女人，她们都在想我！
Hold me!
抱紧我！
Come on, you´ve been dancing enough, come on!
来，你们已经跳够了吧
We need a weight, and you are just right!
我们需要有重量的，你刚好
She can take as much as she weighs.
她足够沉了
Add some more!
再加一点！
Dance, girl! Then l´ll kiss you!
跳啊，女孩儿们！
You can walk in such a shirt in the daylight!
你白天就穿这个吧！
- l will come to show you! - Then better in the night.
- 我会穿给你看！ - 最好能晚上来
Take it, women! l´ll give it all away and add a turban to it as well!
拿好，女孩儿们！头巾，给！
And what devil is this again?
这里又在做什么？
Watch it, bandit, it is flowing on the ground!
看啊，强盗，倒地上了！
Let it flow, the earth drinks gladly too!
没事儿，土也要喝酒！
So generous!
真是慷慨！
Three to Anka, four to Žofka!
三份给Anka，四份给ofka
Fabric like a poppy!
美得像罂粟花
God bless you, son!
上帝保佑你，孩子！
Father Uhorcík... they got him.
Father Uhorck・・・，他被击中了
They played nicely. They played like this on my wedding.
他们跳得很好，就像我婚礼上一样
Quietly, or you will hurt yourself.
不要说话，你会疼的
No, l will be going soon.
我马上就要走了
l only came to thank, ask for forgiveness.
我只是想感谢，希望得到原谅
Father, what´s up with you?
老爹，你怎么了
Nothing, son, it is all right now.
没事了，孩子
l will only rest for a while.
我只是休息一下
Hold me tight.
抱紧我
l will go easier.
这样我好受些
Brothers, say farewell cheerfully.
兄弟们，欢乐地道别吧
Sing me a song for the journey.
为我唱首歌
My song, you know.
我的歌
What´s up with you, horse? Are you sad too?
马儿你也在悲伤吗？
Stop it, or l´ll go crazy.
停下来，我要疯了
- What´s up with you? - What´s up with me?
- 你怎么了？ - 我怎么了？
l see a woman!
我看到了一个女人
- Look who´s coming to us! - l´m hurrying down!
- 看看谁来了 - 我这就下去
- A girl like a lily! - What a miracle!
- 一个像百合一样的姑娘 - 真是漂亮
Where did you find a doe like this?
你在哪里找到的？
She says she´s with us, but she´d bitten my fingers!
她说她是我们一伙的，但是她咬了我的手
Oh, a vixen! l bet she has green eyes!
好一个泼妇，我打赌她眼睛是绿的
- l say they are sky-blue! - Show at least one!
- 我说是天蓝色的 - 至少看一只吧
Come on, womanizer, we will find the way even without you.
少来，登徒子，没你我们也能找到路
Lift your feet, sweetheart, one, the other...
抬起腿，宝贝儿，一步，两步・・・
and now up with your behind!
跳起来
Nice girl.
不错的女孩
When you´ll go back, don´t miss us!
你回去的时候，不要想我们！
Look under your feet, boys, or you´ll go blind!
看好自己脚下！
Shut your eyes! The devil is sending us a temptation.
闭上眼睛，恶魔送来了诱惑
Come here, men! A woman is here!
快来啊，一个女人来了
- Where? What? - She fell from the heaven, lovely!
- 在哪里？ - 她来自天上，太美了
Oh my eyes, don´t fail! l haven´t seen a woman for half a year!
哦，我半年没见过女人了
Take me, girl! l will be carrying you on my arms!
过来吧！我背你！
And you can walk on my head!
你还可以踩到我头上来！
Whose are you, girl?
你是谁的？
Ours, Gregor. Welcome, Terka.
我们的，Gregor， 欢迎，Terka
Thank you.
谢谢
You didn´t have to blindfold her. She is helping us.
不用蒙她的眼睛， 她是来帮我们的
He did well. A woman doesn´t say only what she doesn´t know. The best is a silent woman.
他做得对，女人知道什么都会说出去， 什么都不说的女人最好
- She is silent! - Only when it´s necessary!
- 她什么都不会说！ - 只有必要的时候
She talks...
她会说话
What good have you brought us?
你给我们带了什么？
A writing. For you, Jánošík, from the father.
神父的信
Don´t mess with it, bandit, or you´ll get one.
不要弄，强盗
Listen what our father writes me.
听一下神父的话
The bishop has ordered me to expel you from the church,
主教命令我把你从教堂开除，
deny you the last anointment and a Christian funeral.
你不会有基督徒的葬礼
lt´s bad. l cannot die.
很糟糕，看来我死不了了
And l won´t, just to show the bishop.
我不会死，我要让主教看看
Come, Terka, we will send him a letter.
来，Terka, 我们要给他回信
So, and you´re done with the lady!
所以，你可以在这里见女人！
Girlfriends visit our captain right here.
我们队长的女朋友就可以来
- She was cutting! - She should have been cutting a long time ago.
- 他在自讨苦吃 - 他早就这样了
You will remember this!
你们给我记住
As l say, you need to catch them at sunrise.
你们应该在日出之前抓住他们
Not even a mouse can cross this hole.
这里连老鼠也逃不掉
The forest is thick here, as a fur coat.
这里森林很密，就像皮毛外套
We need to come around Štrbánov hill and below Gápel into the pass.
我们要爬上trbnov山然后走下Gpel才能通过这条路
They light fires on this and on that hill.
他们会在这里和这个山头点火
And what if... you lie?
但是，要是你在说谎呢
You´ve promised one thousand ducats, l´m not a dog!
你们许诺了1000金币，我可不是狗！
A traitor is worse than a mad dog.
叛徒比疯狗更可怕
- ls it him? - l think he knows something.
- 是他吗？ - 我想他知道一些
Or he´s making a fool of you. He hasn´t seen a bandit even in his dreams.
或者他在愚弄你， 他做梦都没见过强盗
Don´t give him a single penny.
一个子儿也不要给他
Jánošík is in the town.
Jáno?ík已经到城里了
This is what my soldiers found on the parish gate.
我的士兵在城门发现的
We will come to say a prayer.
我们一起去做祷告
- What do you think about it? - We will take over the church.
- 你觉得怎么样？ - 我们会占领教堂
Nonsense. They will not come to pray.
没有用，他们不是去祈祷的
Hold the town walls!
守好城墙！
Let this dog go and follow him. A wolf returns to the wolves.
让这条狗滚，然后跟踪他， 一条狼会回到狼群
Free lord from Zochová 150 ducats in silver!
Zochov? 的自由贵族，150银币
Count Dolinay 1 ,000 ducats in gold.
贵族Dolinay，1000金币
Count Cemicayi 500 ducats in silver.
贵族Cemicayi，500银币
Count Lasicayi 300 ducats in silver.
贵族Lasicayi，300银币
Penny-pinch, that Lasicayi.
Lasicayi，守财奴
He drinks everything. And even that they say he borrowed from a Jew.
他把什么都喝光了， 听说他还从一个犹太人那里借了钱
Count Révay 350 ducats in gold...
贵族Rvay，350金币
Count Palucký 800 in silver!
贵族Paluck，800银币
- They´ve been looking for you already. - l haven´t missed anything.
- 他们找了你很久了 - 我知道
We will have Jánošík in chains in an hour.
一小时后Jáno?ík，就会被绑起来
lf he stands there among the monks then even sooner.
如果他在这里，会更快
Free lord from Folkušová 100 ducats in gold...
Folkuov? 来的自由贵族，100金币
Count Zahrayi 300 in gold...
贵族Zahrayi，300金币
Count Boldayi 200 ducats...
贵族Boldayi，200金币
Have you seen how many lords came to the Church?
你看到有多少贵族到这里来了？
- Wait, we´ll go together! - Follow me!
- 我们一起去 - 跟着我
Jánošík is in danger, somebody has to warn him.
Jáno?ík很危险，得有人去警告他
Come, this way.
请跟我来
Praise be to...
奖励是・・・
Jánošík is in the Church!
Jáno?ík在教堂里！
Brute, no, no!
Brute，不要，不要！
For the last time we assure the lordships,
我们最后一次向贵族保证
that the money for the army to fight the bandits, collected by us and sanctified
这些用来资助消灭强盗的钱
will bring to your souls peace and holy satisfaction.
会让你们的灵魂得到安息和宽慰
The silent brothers have brought their offering.
两个不说话的弟兄拿来了他们的奉献
Welcome and accept our bishop´s blessing.
欢迎，请接受我们主教的祝福
We all come to this world in the same way and leave in the same way as well.
我们以同样的方式来到世上， 也会以同样的方式离开
God did not divide people into lords and beggars. That is what we wrote.
上帝没有把人分为贵族和乞丐， 这是我们所写下的话
But you state further on that we are breaking God´s laws,
但是你却说我们违反了上帝的法律
although you know very well that we do not loot for ourselves.
你明明清楚我们不会为了自己而抢劫
That´s why we´ve decided to give this collection too to the poor.
所以我们也要把这些钱分给穷人
Rajcok saw Gajdošík in the town.
Rajcok在城里看到了Gajdok
We took the horses to the lower gate.
我们带这些马去下面的大门
Jánošík is in the town! They´re after Jánošík!
Jáno?ík就在城里，他们在追他！
Stop the bandits! Stop them!
抓住强盗！
Ducats! Pick the ducats!
金币，捡金币啊！
Don´t shoot!
不要射击！
Put out the fire!
把火灭了！
Take the men through the pass to Polská.
带他们去Polsk？
We will meet at Smerdžonka.
我们在Smerdonka见面
With me llcík will stay and...
llck和我留在这里，还有・・・
- And me, captain. - And you, Brute.
- 还有我，队长 - Brute
Go prepare him.
去抓他来
No need for such a hurry.
不用急
Maybe Gajdošík didn´t have time to tell them all.
Gajdok可能还没有告诉他们所有的事
Nothing is moving so far. Men by the fires are on their places.
情况还没变糟， 各个哨岗还有人
What can happen to us...?
还不知道我们会怎么样
Betrayal is worst than death.
背叛比死亡更糟糕
Today - tomorrow they´ll hit us, there´s no way out.
今天，或者明天，他们会来攻打我们， 没有办法了
There is nothing to blame ourselves for and nothing to promise.
我们没有犯错，也没为自己许诺过什么
l know they won´t get a single word from us and we´ll end up as men.
我相信他们不能从我们嘴里问出任何东西， 我们会死得像个男人
Captain, we can resist.
队长，我们可以反抗
- Yes, captain. - Come on, they´ve already dragged him out.
- 是啊，队长 - 他们已经把他拖出来了
He broke the bandit´s vow, betrayed, killed, judge him, fellows.
他违背了我们的誓言， 杀了他，这就是审判
Friends, mercy! l didn´t want to! They induced me!
朋友们，可怜一下我！ 我也不想，是他们引诱我！
For God´s mercy! Don´t shoot!
以上帝的名义！ 不要开枪！
Strengthen the guards and prepare for the leave.
加强守卫，准备好撤离
Protect us and help us, God, protect us from all evil.
保护我们，上帝， 帮助我们远离恶魔
Captain, you are responsible for his life!
队长，你要为他的命负责
Kill the others without mercy!
杀掉剩下的人，不要留情
You can depend on me, he won´t slip Through my fingers this time.
交给我吧，这次他休想逃走
Get down! What is it? You´re stuck?
快下去！怎么了？你被卡住了？
- l forgot my pipe. - Take mine! And move on!
- 我忘了我的绳子 - 用我的，下去吧
- What´s up? - Where are our fellows?
- 怎么了？ - 我们的人呢？
On their heads!
往头上砍！
There he runs!
他跑了！
lt was by the horses.
有马蹄声
Run down, see what´s going on.
我下去看看怎么回事
Stop!
停下！
lt´s him! Don´t shoot!
是他，不要射击！
Follow him!
跟着他！
- Come here! There´s a hole over here. - You better don´t stick your nose into it.
- 过来！这里有个洞！ - 小心你的鼻子
Don´t worry, the rats have left the lair long ago.
不用担心
Goodbye, sweethearts, see you in hell!
再见，去地狱吧
Don´t shoot!
不要开枪！
Don´t shoot, fool!
不要开枪，蠢货！
lnto them!
追上去
Friends, shoot!
朋友们，开枪！
llcík, run!
llck,快跑！
Come on, move up!
快上！
Jesus Christ! llcík! My dearest boy!
上帝！llck！
Who sent you to die here?
是谁杀了你？
l will kill the one...! Who did... Murderers! Who?
谁！是谁？杀人犯！
Jánošík
Jáno?ík
Tereza!
Tereza
- Jánošík, give it up! - No!
- Jáno?ík，投降吧 - 不行！
Wait!
等等！
Tell me where the stolen gold is and l will save you!
告诉我金子到哪里去了， 我会放过你
Only l can give you the emperor´s pardon.
只有我才能让国王放过你
Speak, scamp, or you´ll be sorry!
快说话，不然你会后悔
l am sorry Aurel, that l haven´t killed you long ago.
我后悔没有早杀了你，Aurel
l haven´t killed anybody, but l should have killed you.
我谁都没有杀过， 但是我早该杀了你
- You dog! - l can hear barking!
- 你这条狗！ - 我的确听到了狗叫
lf the count´s honor wouldn´t hold me back, l would crush you like a cockcroach.
要不是为了贵族的荣誉， 我会把你碾碎
- You are tiresome, Aurel! - You will beg like a little child.
- 你真令人厌倦，Aurel - 你会像小孩子一样求我的
Go now!
滚！
The honorable judiciary arrives!
尊敬的法官大人来了！
The court of noble province proposes,
省法庭作出以下判决，
since the offender didn´t reveal at the first torture, where his looted treasure is
由于罪犯没有在第一次讯问中
nor the names of his company has he disclosed,
交代把掠夺的财产藏到了何处， 以及他的组织的命名
the court proposes that he should be subjected to intense torture.
本庭宣判给上动用重刑
l propose to start with the rack.
我主张用架子
Yes.
是
With fire! Good.
要用火
With fire!
烤他！
Because he looted with many fellows,
因为他是和很多同伙一起抢劫
he encouraged the peasants against the lords,
同时煽动农民违抗贵族
he broke divine and secular laws,
他违背的上帝的和世俗的法律
let him be hanged by his rib on a hook as a warning
把他绞死以示众
and in fair torture left to his end!
并且折磨致死
Such punishment will strike all the helpers and supporters,
这样的惩罚可以警告下面的人
every man or woman among the people,
所有男男女女
and young foolish boys,
以及小孩子
who would approve publicly of the actions of the criminal Jánošík,
不要犯Jáno?ík犯下的罪过
or would spread legends about his lootings in any way.
不要行抢劫
Lord Almighty, protect the young man!
万能的上帝！ 请保佑他！
God Almighty, have mercy on him!
上帝，请保佑他！
Hear him in front of your sight...
听到他所说的
Let him to your hearing as you listen to our prayers.
听到我们的祈祷
God Almighty, have mercy on him!
上帝，请保佑他！
Jánošík, listen for the last time!
Jáno?ík， 最后听我说
The emperor will grant you life, if you will use the looted treasures
如果你愿意用抢来的财富组织军队，
to prepare an army against the rebels!
攻打反叛者， 国王会放过你
For the last time! What is your answer to the emperor?
最后一次，你回答我！
Tell him that he is not needed, just like you.
告诉他，人们从来不需要他， 就和你一样
Fires are burning on the mountains!
山上的火正在燃烧
Tell that to your emperor!
告诉你的国王！
Heads up, peasants! Life belongs to us!
大家抬起头来！ 生命是我们的！
One day, the gallows will start blooming.
有一天，绞架会开花